What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today on the
podcast we look at
the best way to control
osteo and rheumatoid arthritis,
and we start with a
look at what happens
when topical olive oil is pitted
against an ibuprofen type drug.
Fifty million Americans
suffer from arthritis,
and osteoarthritis of the knee
is the most common form,
making it a leading
cause of disability.
Several inflammatory pathways
underlie the onset and
progression of the disease,
and so various anti-inflammatory
foods have been put to the test.
Strawberries decrease the
levels circulating in the blood
of an inflammatory mediator
known as tumor necrosis factor,
but that doesn’t necessarily
translate into clinical improvement.
For example, drinking
cherry juice can lower a sign
of inflammation known
as C-reactive protein,
but it failed to help with the disease.
But wait, it says
“provided symptom relief.”
Yeah, it did, but no better than
placebo, meaning drinking it
was essentially no better
than doing nothing.
Cherries may help with another
kind of arthritis called gout,
but they failed when it
came to osteoarthritis.
The same with pomegranate juice.
No significant improvement
in symptoms, but then again,
no significant improvement in
inflammatory mediators either;
so, perhaps there’s no surprise.
But strawberries did
decrease inflammation.
Let’s see if they actually
help in a randomized,
double-blind cross-over trial, and . . .
dietary strawberries were
indeed found to have a significant
analgesic effect, causing a
significant decrease in pain.
There are tumor necrosis factor
inhibitor drugs on the market
now available for the low, low
cost of only about $40,000 a year.
For that kind of money, you’d want
some really juicy side effects,
and they do not disappoint,
like an especially fatal lymphoma.
I think I’ll stick with the strawberries.
One of the reasons we suspected
berries might help is that
if you give people the
equivalent of either a cup a day
of blueberries, or two
cups a day of strawberries,
and then drip their blood
onto cells in a petri dish,
you can see a significant
blunting of inflammation
compared to those who
got placebo berries.
And note that the attenuation of
inflammation got better with time,
so apparently the longer
you eat berries the better.
Are there any other foods
that have been tested in this way?
Researchers in France harvested
cartilage from knee replacement
surgeries and then exposed
them to concentrates of the blood
of volunteers who
took a whopping dose
of a grapeseed and olive extract.
They saw a significant drop
of induced inflammation.
There haven’t been any human
studies putting grapeseeds
to the test for arthritis,
but an olive extract was shown
to decrease pain and
improve daily activities
in osteoarthritis sufferers.
So, does this mean adding olive
oil to one’s diet may help?
No, because they used freeze-
dried olive vegetation water.
That’s basically what’s left
over after you extract the oil
from the olives; it’s all
the water-soluble components.
In other words, it’s all
the stuff that’s in an olive
that‘s missing from olive oil.
If you give people actual olives,
a dozen large green olives a day,
you can see a before versus after
drop in an inflammatory mediator.
What if you look only at the oil?
A systematic review and meta-analysis
on the anti-inﬂammatory
beneﬁts of olive oil
found there does not appear to be any.
But wait, what about papers
that ascribe remarkable
anti-inflammatory effects
to extra virgin olive oil?
Here’s their evidence on. . . rodents.
In people, extra virgin olive oil
may be no better than butter
when it comes to inflammation,
and worse than even coconut oil.
So, should we just stick to olives?
Sadly, a dozen olives a day
could take up nearly half
your sodium limit for the entire day.
When put to the test, extra virgin
olive oil did not appear
to help with fibromyalgia
symptoms either,
but it did work better than canola oil
in alleviating symptoms of
inflammatory bowel disease.
Unfortunately, I couldn’t find
any studies putting olive oil
intake to the test for arthritis.
But wait, why is this video entitled
Extra Virgin Olive Oil for Arthritis?
Because (are you ready for this?)
it appears to work topically.
A double-blind, randomized,
clinical trial of topical
virgin olive oil versus a gel
containing an ibuprofen-type
drug for osteoarthritis of the knee.
Just a gram of oil, which
would be like less than
a quarter teaspoon, three times a day.
So that would cost less than
three cents a day and… it worked!
Topical olive oil was significantly better
than the drug in reducing pain.
And the study only lasted a
month, so maybe the olive oil
would have continued to work
better and better over time.
What about the effectiveness
of olive oil in controlling
morning inflammatory pain
of fingers and knees
among women with
rheumatoid arthritis?
The researchers went all
out, comparing the use of
extra virgin olive oil, to
just rubbing on nothing,
to rubbing on that
ibuprofen-type gel, and evidently
the decrease in the
disease activity score
in the olive oil group beat out the others.
In our next story, pomegranates
are put to the test for weight loss,
diabetes, COPD, prostate cancer,
osteoarthritis, and rheumatoid arthritis.
In a landmark case that made
it all the way up to the
U.S. Court of Appeals before
being denied review
by the Supreme Court, POM Wonderful
(the pomegranate juice company)
vs. Federal Trade Commission, a
panel of judges concluded that
many of POM’s ads made
misleading or false claims
touting medical studies ostensibly
showing that pomegranate products
could help treat various ailments,
including heart disease,
prostate cancer, and erectile dysfunction,
and the First Amendment does not protect
deceptive and misleading advertisements.
Striking a blow to its billionaire
owners, the Court ruled
that at least one randomized
clinical trial could be required
to substantiate any claims of
treating or preventing disease.
If you look at the medical literature
on the benefits of pomegranates
in general on the “medicinal effects of pomegranate.”
But if you dig a little deeper
you see this is based on studies
like this: “antiobesity effects
of pomegranate leaf extract
in a mouse model.”
First of all, who eats pomegranate leaves?
And second of all, who’s a mouse?
And if you do have a fat pet mouse,
maybe just feed them less lard.
Does pomegranate consumption
affect weight in humans?
If you look at all the
randomized controlled clinical trials
(meaning human trials), pomegranates
have no significant effect
on body weight, BMI, belly fat,
or even body fat percentage
in those randomized to
pomegranate product consumption.
What about for the prevention and
treatment of cardiovascular diseases?
Researchers reviewed 25 clinical
trials, looking at cholesterol,
blood pressure, artery function,
atherosclerotic plaque formation,
and platelet function, and...
even in the best studies,
they did not find significant
indications of benefit.
Here’s a study on pomegranate
juice and erectile dysfunction.
It was funded by the POM company,
and yet it failed as well.
No benefit for diabetes
markers and no benefit
for chronic obstructive pulmonary
diseases like emphysema.
They were banking on the antioxidant
activity of pomegranate juice
to help, but that’s antioxidant activity in vitro
(meaning in a test tube or petri dish).
To my surprise, a meta-analysis
of data from 11 randomized
controlled trials did not
support convincing evidence
of pomegranate intake having a
significant increasing effect
on total antioxidant
capacity of your bloodstream
because some of the
most potent antioxidants
don’t even seem to be
absorbed into the human body.
No wonder pomegranate supplementation
didn’t seem to affect
oxidative stress in tissue samples
taken from prostate cancer patients.
But, of course, what we care about is whether
it affects the cancer Itself.
The strongest evidence for the
anticancer activity of pomegranates
is said to come from
studies on prostate cancer.
Unfortunately, early promising
results were not conﬁrmed
when they were actually put to the test.
For example, daily pomegranate intake
was found in a randomized
controlled trial to have
no impact on PSA levels,
a marker of tumor progression.
And, indeed, a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
found essentially no
difference when it came to
prostate cancer disease progression.
They were banking on the anti-
inflammatory activity of
pomegranate juice to help, but again,
that had been demonstrated in vitro.
In people, a meta-analysis based
on five randomized controlled trials
published in 2016 concluded
that pomegranate juice did not
have a significant effect on
C-reactive protein levels,
a key marker of inflammation.
If you look at the forest
plot, though, you’ll see
all five trials tended towards
lower C-reactive protein levels
such that the data combined almost
reached statistical significance.
And indeed, an updated meta-
analysis published in 2020
based on seven studies
did indeed get tipped over into
significance and found a significant drop
in two other inflammatory markers as well.
Huh, okay. Well, maybe
pomegranate juice could help
in the control of inﬂammatory
diseases after all.
But you don’t know...until you put it to the test.
Osteoarthritis involves the degeneration
of the cushioning cartilage
within joints, particularly the knees.
If you take some human
osteoarthritic cartilage samples
and drip on a pomegranate extract,
you can show cartilage-protective effects.
Here’s how much cartilage disintegration
was happening at baseline.
Add some inflammation and
cartilage breakdown triples,
but then add more and more
of this pomegranate extract,
and you can calm things down.
But again, that’s in a petri dish.
How do we know that when
we eat pomegranates,
the active components actually
get into our bloodstream
so they can find their way into our joints?
Cartilage-protecting components
were found to be bioavailable
(at least in rabbits), raising the
possibility that pomegranates
could be a safe and non-toxic
treatment with no side effects,
as opposed to the drugs currently
in use. But is it effective?
Clinical trials are in progress,
and so many questions
will be answered...right now!
The first and only clinical trial to date
on pomegranate juice and osteoarthritis.
It’s not a placebo-controlled trial,
but instead randomized people
to pomegranate juice or nothing at all.
Those drinking the juice did report
less stiffness and impairment
of physical function, but
not significantly better
than just doing nothing. Shoot.
But just as I was about to give up
on pomegranates, I saw this study:
Consumption of a pomegranate
extract suppresses joint damage
in rheumatoid arthritis. But no...
it was just the POM
‘Not-So-Wonderful’ company
inducing joint damage in a mouse
as a model of rheumatoid
arthritis. Come on!
What about this open-labeled study,
where the patients knew
what they were getting?
Eight people with active
rheumatoid arthritis took some
pomegranate extract every day,
and the six who stuck with it
reported fewer tender joints.
But as we learned from
the osteoarthritis study,
if you don’t have a control group you
have no sense at all of what role,
if any, the treatment actually plays.
So finally, we come to this:
a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial. It’s about time!
Half of the subjects unknowingly
got some pomegranate extracts;
the other half unknowingly got the
equivalent of a sugar pill and...
significant improvement in
the number of swollen joints,
tender joints, pain intensity,
a disease activity score,
a health assessment questionnaire,
and morning stiffness
compared to placebo. So, if you
have rheumatoid arthritis,
I would indeed recommend you
start eating pomegranates.
Why not just pop pomegranate pills?
After all, it was a pomegranate extract
that alleviated disease activity.
One good reason to stick to the
fruit is that when 19 pomegranate
supplements were actually tested in a laboratory,
most didn’t actually appear to have
any pomegranate in them at all!
Only 6 out of 19 appeared
to be authentic.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.